Grunwald Gallery of Art records, 1970-2015 C581
Indiana University Archives
Grunwald Gallery of Art records
1970-2015
1990-2015
Indiana University Archives
Grunwald Gallery of Art
C581
4 cubic feet 4 boxes
Since 1983, the Grunwald Gallery of Art, formerly the School of Fine Arts Gallery (SoFA), has presented contemporary works by both professional and student artists in a special exhibition format. The records in this collection include exhibition publicity, audio and visual materials, and photographic slides spanning 1970-2015.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Advance notice is required.
Administrative History
The Grunwald Gallery of Art, formerly the School of Fine Arts (SoFA) Gallery presents contemporary works by both professional and student artists in a special exhibition format. The SoFA Gallery began in 1983 when the IU Art Museum moved to its new building and vacated over 5200 square feet of exhibit space. The first few years of the Gallery featured intermittent shows curated by faculty in studio and art history until 1987 when the University established a part-time gallery director position.
In 2011, the SoFA Gallery was renamed the Grunwald Gallery of Art in honor of John A. Grunwald, thanks to a significant endowed gift from his widow, Rita Grunwald. John A. Grunwald (1935-2006) was born in Budapest, Hungary, to Jewish parents. He survived the Holocaust in Europe, and came to New York in 1950. Grunwald graduated with a degree in Economics from Indiana University in 1956, and met his wife Rita during that time. Both Mr. and Mrs. Grunwald were deeply interested in art, and frequently attended SoFA Gallery openings, exhibitions, and discussions. Rita Grunwald worked in the Fine Arts building for about 25 years, both in the Bookshop, and also as a Friend of the Art member.
Today, the mission of the Grunwald Gallery is to present contemporary art by significant regional and nationally known artists, as well as by faculty and students within the school. Exhibits incorporate art from a variety of contemporary genres and approaches, and can be experimental or traditional. The Gallery is conceived as a visual arts laboratory with artists participating in the installation of their works and interaction with students and the public is encouraged. As the Grunwald Gallery frequently collaborates with artists, scientists and scholars, this results in the production of exhibits that interpret visual art in a broader scientific or humanities context. The temporary exhibit format provides the Gallery with flexibility to respond to opportunities and directions in the contemporary art world, allowing programming to evolve based on current trends and directions. The Gallery hosts over thirty exhibits annually of students from Indiana University's Henry Radford Hope School of Fine Arts, focusing on work by advanced undergraduate, BFA and MFA students.
Arrangement
Collection is organized into three series: Exhibition publicity (1990-2015, undated), Audio/Visual Materials (1970-2012, undated), and Slides (1983-2005, undated).
Scope and Content Note
This collection is organized into three series: Exhibition publicity (1990-2015, undated), Audio/Visual Materials (1970-2012, undated), and Slides (1983-2005, undated).
Materials in the Exhibition publicity series include post cards, calendars, oversize posters, and pamphlets describing exhibitions at the Grunwald Gallery of Art; they are organized chronologically first by decade, then by year. Records in the Audio/Visual Materials series include audio-cassettes, video-cassettes, and DVDs of lectures, exhibitions, and interviews related to the Grunwald Gallery of Art. Materials in the Slides series include slides and prints of slides, all relating to exhibitions held at the Grunwald Gallery of Art.
Separated Material
Note: Oversized posters housed separately.
Related Material
Additional records such as newsletters, annual reports, bulletins, and publications may be accessed in the Archives of Institutional Memory.
Archived web sites for the Grunwald Gallery may be included in Archive-It.
Related photographs may be available in the University Archives Photographs Database.
Acquisition Information
Accession: 2015/026
Provenance
Transferred to the IU Archives in February 2015 by Grunwald Gallery Director, Betsy Stirratt.
College art museums--Indiana--Bloomington--History--Sources.; College art museums--Public relations--Indiana--Bloomington--History--Sources.; Art--Indiana--Bloomington--History--Sources.; Grunwald Gallery of Art -- Archives; Grunwald Gallery of Art -- Records and correspondence
- Exhibition Publicity, 1990-2015; undated (Box 1)
  - undated (Box 1)
  - 1990 (Box 1)
  - 1991 (Box 1)
  - 1992 (Box 1)
  - 1993 (Box 1)
  - 1994 (Box 1)
  - 1995 (Box 1)
  - 1996 (Box 1)
  - 1997 (Box 1)
  - 1998 (Box 1)
  - 1999 (Box 1)
  - 2000 (Box 1)
  - 2001 (Box 1)
  - 2002 (Box 1)
  - 2003 (Box 1)
  - 2004 (Box 1)
  - 2005 (Box 1)
  - 2006 (Box 1)
  - 2007 (Box 1)
  - 2008 (Box 1)
  - 2009 (Box 1)
  - 2010 (Box 1)
  - 2011 (Box 1)
    General
    (Oversized posters housed separately)
  - 2012 (Box 1)
  - 2013 (Box 1)
  - 2014 (Box 1)
  - 2015 (Box 1)
- Audio/Visual Materials, 1970-2012; undated
  - Audio Materials, 1995 (Box 1)
    - Audio-cassette (Box 1)
      - "Interview with David Ebbinghouse from WFIU 12458", 8/24/1995; genreform: Type 1 analog audio cassette: (Box 1)
        Online Streaming in Media Collections Online
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/hd76sg649
  - Visual Materials, 1970-2012; undated (Box 1)
    - 12 DVDs, (2002-2012) (Box 1)
      - Grunwald Gallery Naming Ceremony, 9/2/2011 (Box 1)
        (3 copies)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/xw42nr86t
      - "Human Nature I: The Natural World" Alexis Rockman, 10/20/2006 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/n583zb94d
      - "Human Nature II: Future Worlds", Eduardo Kac, 2/9/2007 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/0z709c84h
      - Q & A Session, last Folio: A Discussion with Yuri Dojc and Katy Krausova, 2/2/2011 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/0v838g67m
      - "Selling It or Giving It Away: A Discussion about Tissue Research, Ownership and Consent", 3/8/2007 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/6h4418931
      - "Small Is Big", Catherine Kehoe, 10/23/2012 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/gf06gm04f
      - "Trash Can", Barry Anderson, 10/11/2003 (Box 1)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/js956z54w
      - "Yearning for a Golden Age", Barry Anderson, 4/2002 (Box 1)
    - 35 Video-cassettes, (1970-2001; undated) (Box 2)
      - "Bruce Nauman Lip Sync", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        No sleeve
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/c534g583s
      - "Holly Hughes and some Annie Sprinkle", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/bz60dd00f
      - "Lazansky Panel, Original 9/10 Art Lecture", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/6969zh88r
      - "Linda Wiley, Part I and Part II", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/dr26zd81g
      - "Martha Rosler, The Strange Case of Baby M", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/bg257z05k
      - "Nam June Paik", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/k930cd325
      - "Save Golub", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/9w032m00k
      - "'Shooting Back' Photo Exhibit/Lecture", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/4f16ck88h
      - "Shooting Back: Photography by Homeless Children" Robin Smith, undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/08613506h
      - "Vito Acconci: The Red Tapes", undated; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/bz60dd01q
      - "Andy Warhol/Paul Morrisey, Trash", 1970; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/6t053z75x
      - "Video Art, 1982-1991", Jim Manion, genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        Also contains a list of the 10 shorts on the video.
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/9w032k991
      - "Portrait of an Artist at Work: Cindy Sherman", 1984; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/rn301j545
      - "Smedberg Low Budget Side Dishes, 1987 [and] Ten Ideas That Will Revolutionize Auilization [?], 1988", 1987-1988; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/1z40m918s
      - "Art Lecture, Joel Peter Witkin, Zoom Pictures-331-7659", 11/9/1989; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        (2 copies)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/g158c105n
      - "James Rosati: Ode VI", 1989; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/df65vr23s
      - "Jenny Holzer, Televised Text", 1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/2801pz86k
      - "The Lull Before the Storm, Part 1 and 2", Sara Diamond, 1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/w0892t67n
      - "Marjorie K. Schick, Number 1", 1/17/1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/nc5815007
      - "Marjorie K. Schick, Number 2", 1/17/1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
      - "Marjorie K. Schick, Number 3", 1/17/1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
      - Sue Coe Lecture (copy), 11/8/1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
      - Sue Coe Lecture, IU School of Fine Arts Auditorium, 11/8/1990; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/j6731m531
      - "Studio Six featuring: The Shooting Back Exhibit, Betsy Stirratt, Fine Arts Gallery", 11/19/1992; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/wp989264t
      - "Those Fluttering Objects of Desire," Shu Lea Chang, 1992; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/3n204f49f
      - "Andrew Serrano Lecture & Interview", 2/26/1994; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/79408d667
      - "Andrew Serrano Lecture & Interview" (dub), 2/26/1994; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
      - Betye & Alison Saar "Conjure Women of the Arts.", 1994; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/zk51w073s
      - "Carrie Mae Weems Lecture", 2/10/1995; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/ff365n86v
      - "A Dialogue Through Objects, 1960-1996", Isaac Monteiro, genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        Also contains typed and signed letter from Isaac Monteiro.
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/2z10x701g
      - "Kuspit Lecture", 10/15/1999; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/5h73qd04j
      - "Barry Anderson, Mark Beebe, Richard Saxton", 9/21/2001; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/9k41zx62f
      - "Richard Saxton", 9/21/2001; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/m613nf17p
      - "Vito Acconci Theme Song", 1973; genreform: VHS cassette: (Box 2)
        https://media.dlib.indiana.edu/media_objects/8c97m7153
- Slides, 1983-2005; undated (Box 3)
  - Untitled, undated (Box 3)
  - 1000 Kisses, 19 Oct.-17 Nov. 2001 (Box 3)
  - The Art of Desire: Erotic Treasures from the Kinsey Institute, undated (Box 3)
  - Sylvia Plath, undated (Box 3)
  - 1983-1988 (Box 3)
    (2 folders)
  - 1986 and, 1988-1991 (Box 3)
    (4 folders)
  - 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - 1991-1995 (Box 3)
  - 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  - 1997-1999 (Spring) (Box 4)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 4)
    (3 folders)
  - 1999 (Box 4)
  - 1999-2000 (Box 4)
  - 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - 2001-2002 (Box 4)
  - 2002-2003 (Box 4)
  - 2003-2005 (Box 4)